A Guide to the Rockefeller family Associates, Berent Friele papers FA468
Rockefeller Archive Center
- General Correspondence, 2; 2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller Center for Social Science, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    Concerns correspondence and details for the building of the Nelson A. Rockefeller Center for Social Science at Dartmouth College in memory of the late Vice President. Contains a pamphlet with the building plans and information.
  - New York State 350th Anniversary Hudson-Champlain, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    A memorandum on the 350th anniversary of the expeditions of explorers Henry Hudson and Samuel de Champlain and the celebrations to take place in honor of them in Governor Nelson Rockefeller's newly dedicated "Year of History". Contains facts and information pertaining to the celebration as well as preparations to be made.
  - "P" and "R" Correspondence, 1957-1968 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    Letters and messages passed between Berent Friele and his associates with last names going from P through R. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Partners of the Americas, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    Involves correspondence, pamphlets, and information regarding a program affiliated with Friele and Nelson Rockefeller which seeks to promote partnership by pairing regions of Latin America with individual states of the United States. Also includes letter from President Jimmy Carter congratulating the President of Partners of the Americas on his organization's achievements.
  - Peruvian Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    Contains letter written by David Rockefeller to Peruvian economist and politician Pedro Beltran along with a thank you note to Nelson Rockefeller for inviting Friele and his wife to a party
  - Alvaro Ponce, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    Contains personal correspondence relating to Alvaro Ponce, son-in-law of Galo Plaza.
  - President-Elect Costa e Silva and David Rockefeller, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    A single letter addressed to Berent Friele from a Brazilian dignitary, Jorge Paes de Carvalho, concerning several Brazilian statesmen visiting the United States and arranging a meeting for them with David and Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Rio Museum of Modern Art, 1956-1964 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    Includes correspondence between Berent Friele and one Jorge Paes de Carvalho, treasurer of the Rio Museum of Modern Art (MAM), about a recent shipment of glass to the museum which was broken in transit and needs to be replaced. Contains further correspondence regarding contributions and donations towards the museum's founding. Includes photographs of museum in stages of development.
  - Rockefellers, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Rodman Rockefeller, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    Includes photographs and personal letters and correspondence from Rodman Rockefeller. Also includes a speech by Rodman Rockefeller delivered while he was President of IBEC (International Basic Economy Corporation).
  - Rodman Rockefeller: Photographs, 1975 (Box 19, Folder 254)
  - Ski for Light Program, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    Friele's correspondence with persons involved in the Ski for Light program which involves promoting ski touring in Norway, in particular for the benefit of the the visually impaired and blind. Includes photos and pamphlet. The program was promoted by Rockefeller resorts such as Woodstock, Vermont as seen in a letter from Friele to Laurance Rockefeller.
  - Stephen Low, 1970-1980 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    Includes correspondence with Stephen Low, a member of the Department of State and Ambassador to Zambia. Includes pictures and postcards.
  - Anne- Marie R. Krogstad, 1959-1971 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    Includes correspondence and clippings concerning Anne-Marie Rockefeller Krogstad.
  - Steven C. Rockefeller Photographs, 1966-1975 (Box 19, Folder 255)
  - Summer Brazil Trip, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    Correspondence and files pertaining to Berent Friele's visit to Brazil in the summer of 1950. Includes many documents discussing IBEC's affairs in Brazil as well as other business endeavors.
  - Trip to Brazil General and Personal, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 95)
    A large assortment of correspondence, letters, and memorandums related to Berent Friele's 1952 visit to Brazil, primarily of a personal nature. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Tumucmumaque, 1968-1971 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    Correspondence and photographs pertaining to a large forest preserve called Tumucumaque National Park located in Brazil.
  - Tumucmumaque: Photographs, 1968-1971 (Box 19, Folder 256)
  - University of the Andes, 1958-1982 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    Correspondence and programs pertaining to the University of the Andes Foundation and the contributions of Berent Friele and others to its development.
  - "V" Correspondence, 1953-1970 (Box 6, Folder 98)
    Letters and messages passed between Berent Friele and his associates with last names beginning with V. Contains an article with an obituary for recently deceased Brazilian President Vargas. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Victor Andrade and David Rockefeller, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    Includes correspondence to Berent Friele and David Rockefeller from Victor Andrade concerning a memorial ceremony held for Nelson Rockefeller.
  - "W" Correspondence, 1956-1973 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    Letters and messages passed between Berent Friele and his associates with last names beginning with W. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - William B. Wimpenney, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 101)
    The resume and curriculum vitae of one William B. Wimpenney, a businessman and manager who had applied for a position at IBEC.
  - Winthrop Rockefeller, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 102)
    Includes brief correspondence between Berent Friele and Winthrop Rockefeller regarding congratulations over Winthrop's gubernatorial victory in Arkansas.
- Nelson A. Rockefeller Correspondence, 3; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
  Correspondence between Nelson A. Rockefeller and Berent Friele of both a business and personal nature.
  - AIFLD and Nelson Rockefeller, 1962-1980 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    Includes minutes of the annual board meeting for the AIFLD on which Nelson Rockefeller served. Topics of discussion include threat of communism in Latin America primarily stemming from Cuba. Includes statement of the AIFLD budget for 1978-1979 and newspaper clippings.
  - Albert H. McNutt, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    Contains letters from one Albert McNutt to Nelson Rockefeller regarding a civil engineering project in Latin America which he believes Nelson may be interested it. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Brazilian Conference Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    Correspondence between Nelson Rockefeller and Berent Friele among other associates concerning Latin American affairs, primarily the Bi-National Brazilian Conference hosted by the Council on Foreign Relations.
  - Brazilian Memos to Governor, 1959-1970 (Box 7, Folder 106)
    Contains several memos to Nelson Rockefeller concerning developments in Brazil, including the appointment of a new US Ambassador to Brazil, William Rountree, as well as several visits to the US by Brazilian dignitaries. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Election Congratulations, 1966-1970 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    Several telegrams drafted by Friele and sent by Nelson Rockefeller to a few recently elected presidents in various Latin American republics, including Costa Rica and Colombia.
  - Elections, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    Contains documents pertaining to recent presidential elections in Brazil and Panama as well as newspaper articles. Also includes correspondence regarding contemporary Latin American events and visits between Nelson A. Rockefeller and one Walther Moreira Salles, a notable Brazilian banker and politician.
  - Fazenda Bodoquena, 1956-1967 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    Documents related to Nelson A. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, and the Fazenda Bodoquena.
  - Margaretta (Happy) F. Rockefeller, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Margaretta (Happy) F. Rockefeller, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    Contains letter from Happy Rockefeller to Berent Friele thanking him for his condolences about Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Margaretta (Happy) F. Rockefeller and OAS, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 112)
    Contains a single note from Happy Rockefeller to Berent Friele regarding a statue given to the Organization of American States in memory of Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Margaretta (Happy) F. Rockefeller, 1974-1977 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Henry A. Kissinger, 1970-1980 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Hugh Morrow and Public Affairs, 1966-1975 (Box 7, Folder 115)
    Includes many various correspondences with Hugh Morrow, one of Nelson's advisors and speech-writers, regarding the public affairs relevant to Nelson Rockefeller and Berent Friele's interests.
  - IBEC in Brazil, 1972-1977 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    Contains a note to Friele from Governor Nelson Rockefeller exclaiming his amazement at the fact that seemingly everyone in Brazil is associated with and adores Friele.
  - Miscellaneous Nelson Rockefeller Memos, 1959-1970 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    Includes a variety of letters sent mostly from Berent Friele to Nelson Rockefeller as advice and current events primarily focusing on Latin America. Most letters serve as briefs of state business, particularly in the realm of international relations. Contains newspaper clippings. Contains large photo of Nelson and Mrs. Rockefeller accompanying King Frederik IX and Queen Ingrid of Denmark.
  - Miscellaneous Nelson Rockefeller Memos: Photographs, 1959-1970 (Box 19, Folder 257)
  - Mission to Brazil, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    Correspondence between Nelson Rockefeller and Berent Friele regarding recent elections in Brazil as well as the official US mission to the country.
  - Narfarms Del Ecuador, 1960-1970 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    Includes correspondence regarding Nelson Rockefeller and Berent Friele's affairs in Ecuador, especially concerning a Hacienda undergoing labor troubles representative of communism. Also includes many letters and correspondences regarding coffee production at Narfarms del Ecuador, a model farm established by Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1953-1968 (Box 7, Folder 120)
    An assortment of letters and news press about Nelson A. Rockefeller's visit to Brazil, particularly concerning his associate, Brazilian news magnate Assis Chateaubriand. Also contains news press about a new military assistance pact between the United States and Brazil. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1964-1973 (Box 7, Folder 121)
    A large assortment of various letters, correspondence, memos, and speeches generally relating to Nelson Rockefeller and President Medici of Brazil and either written to or by Berent Friele. Notably contains a confidential memorandum by the Conference of Latin American Chancellors for Continental Cooperation on bases for a new dialogue between Latin America and the United States. Also contains eulogy delivered by Nelson at the funeral of his younger brother, Winthrop. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller Visit to Brazil, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 122)
    Includes an itinerary for Nelson Rockefeller's 1952 visit to Brazil as well as a list of dignitaries with whom he met during his trip. Includes notes for a meeting with future President of Brazil Juscelino Kubitschek.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Trip, 1976-1979 (Box 7, Folder 123)
    Details of a trip taken to Brazil.
  - Nelson Rockefeller and Janio Quadros, 1955-1963 (Box 7, Folder 124)
    Correspondence and press related to Janio Quadros, President of Brazil. Notably includes a memorandum to Nelson Rockefeller from Berent Friele containing detailed notes of a meeting between himself and Quadros. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Nelson Rockefeller and President Betancourt Visit, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    Correspondence and documents pertaining to the visit of the President of Venezuela Betancourt to the United States and the home of Nelson Rockefeller. Includes notes taken from a press conference upon Betancourt's arrival. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Nelson Rockefeller-Berent Friele Correspondence, 1952-1975 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    Primarily correspondence between Nelson Rockefeller and Berent Friele, but also including several messages to Friele from other associates such as Galo Plaza. Includes newspaper clippings and condolences for death of Nelson's father, John D. Rockefeller Jr. Also includes notable dialogue concerning "Coffee-Wheat and Psychological Warfare" which is plan to import surplus coffee from Brazil into US in exchange for surplus wheat. Includes short biography of Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 127)
    An assortment of letters and messages to and from Nelson A. Rockefeller which primarily concern interests in Latin America.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Death, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 128)
    Assorted letters and messages all relating to the death of Nelson Rockefeller, mostly addressed to Berent Friele.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Memorial, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 129)
    A large compilation of various newspaper articles and letters regarding the construction of a memorial to Nelson Rockefeller as well as Claude C. Erb's dissertation on Nelson and US-Latin American affairs. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Memos, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    Various memos and notes to Nelson Rockefeller from Berent Friele giving advice and reminding him of important dates.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Personal Letters, 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 131)
    A few thank-you letters sent from Nelson to Berent Friele and his wife, Jenny. Also an apology letter from Nelson concerning their cancellation of a planned visit to Brazil.
  - Nelson Rockefeller Presidential Mission, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    Includes speech by Berent Friele delivered at Brazilian-American Chamber of Commerce luncheon and other correspondence regarding US-Brazilian relations.
  - News Clippings, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    Includes newspaper clippings relating to various Rockefeller family members, but primarily Nelson A. Rockefeller. Also focuses in large part on Brazilian efforts to enhance paper and pulp industry.
  - Office of the Vice President, 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 134)
    Contains many documents and letters relating to an organization focused on promoting Hispanic businesses. Also contains letter from a Cuban exile to Nelson Rockefeller who wishes to see Nelson elected to the White House because he believes Nelson can "free Cuba". Many letters asking for support of Nelson Rockefeller for various projects, initiatives, forms of assistance, etc. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Organization of American States and Nelson Rockefeller, 1980-1984 (Box 8, Folder 135)
    A variety of correspondence relating to Nelson Rockefeller and his association with bettering relations between the US and Latin America, including many letters from Ecuadorian President Galo Plaza. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 136)
    Assorted letters and messages of a personal nature written most often between Nelson Rockefeller and Berent Friele. Also includes speech by Secretary of State Henry Kissinger in Brazil.
  - Pocantico Party, 1976-1979 (Box 9, Folder 137)
    A letter from Berent Friele to Governor Nelson Rockefeller regarding a party he is hosting which will include Brazilian notables among the guests.
  - Postponed Brazil Visit, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 138)
    Correspondence and messages relating to a postponed visit to Brazil by Nelson Rockefeller and his wife, Happy. Includes newspaper clippings and photographs.
  - Saved Newspapers, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 139)
    A compilation of newspapers with articles on important current events as well as news concerning the Rockefeller family, primarily Nelson. Features an opinion piece about Fidel Castro written in both English and Spanish.
  - Saved Newspapers, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 140)
    A large compilation of newspapers in a variety of languages covering press primarily related to Nelson Rockefeller.
  - Soviet Correspondence, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 141)
    Includes a letter by Friele written on behalf of Nelson Rockefeller which asks for the Soviet ambassador (Anatoliy Dobrynin) to approve a visa for a woman who appealed to him in order to marry a Soviet national.
  - Thank-You Notes, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 142)
    Thank-you notes from Berent Friele to Nelson Rockefeller regarding party invitations.
  - The Pan American Society of the United States Inc., 1977 (Box 9, Folder 143)
    Includes invitation and photographic newsletter of Pan American Society Gold Medal Luncheon celebrating Nelson Rockefeller. Letters written to Berent Friele typically regarding Pan American Society. Also includes a letter written by Nelson Rockefeller in which he rejects invitation to become Honorary President of the Pan American Society.
  - Vice President Nelson Rockefeller Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 144)
    Various letters of correspondence concerning Vice President Nelson Rockefeller and usually composed by Berent Friele in communication with associates of his and Nelson's. Many of the letters are requests for assistance in seeking employment and include attached resumes.
  - Victor Andrade, 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 145)
    A large file with various forms of correspondence and association between Nelson Rockefeller and Victor Andrade, a Bolivian Ambassador. Includes a lengthy memoir by Andrade on his initial meeting with and friendship with Nelson in which he gives credit to Nelson for pushing the US Government to take an interest in the lives of the Bolivian working class responsible for mining the tin fueling the US war effort in the Second World War. Contains several resumes.
- Business, Corporate, and Political Files, 4; 4.27 Cubic Feet 10 letter document boxes and 1 legal document box
  Documents, files, and memoranda pertaining to the many businesses and corporations with which Berent Friele was affiliated. Also focuses on the political activities of Berent Friele, and such activites conducted by Friele on behalf of others. Includes some published articles on these businesses.
  - "A Qualidade De Vida Nas Americas", 1970 (Box 10, Folder 146)
  - ACCION and Partners of the Americas, 1980-1982 (Box 10, Folder 147)
    Contains a length minutes report on a meeting held by the board of directors of Accion International as well as other material related to the organization. Also contains material concerning the organization Partners of the Americas. Contains financial statements and figures.
  - AIFLD and Brazil, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 148)
    Information on the goings on of AIFLD activities in Brazil primarily concerned with labor-management cooperation among the Brazilians. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development, 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 149)
    An assortment of documents and correspondence related to the AIFLC. Includes newspaper clippings, pamphlets of the organization, and financial statements within director meeting minutes.
  - Americas Foundation, 1947-1980 (Box 10, Folder 150)
    Further correspondence and events hosted by the Americas Foundation involving Berent Friele. Contains remarks made by Nelson Rockefeller in 1947 at a dinner honoring President of Mexico Miguel Aleman Valdes.
  - Americas Foundation, 1980-1982 (Box 10, Folder 151)
    Contains a pamphlet titled "The Birthday of the Americas Dinner", held by the Americas Foundation, which includes information on the celebration as well as an itinerary for the evening. Contains remarks and speeches pertaining to Alberto Lleras, President of Colombia. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Aracruz Celulose, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 152)
    A long, bound memorandum for the company Aracruz Celulose proposing the business plan for a $40,000,000 investment in the company's project, which primarily concerns forestry-work and pulp manufacturing. Includes balance sheets and photographs of Aracruz Celulose's plant in Brazil as well as several unattached photographs of involved person and a pamphlet for the company.
  - Asesoria Dinamica a Microempresas, A.C., 1980 (Box 10, Folder 153)
    A packet which details the economic needs of a region of Mexico. Includes newspaper clippings. Also includes the minutes of a meeting of the board of directors of ACCION International.
  - Brazil and IBEC, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 154)
    Materials related to IBEC's endeavors in Brazil including the production of a new seed-hybrid variant of corn to be grown in the agricultural regions of the country.
  - Brazil and Interamericana, 1952-1953 (Box 10, Folder 155)
    Contains business correspondence on Interamericana, a finance and investment firm based in South America, including stock returns and other profit statements. Many files contain information on projected profits of investment banks in Latin American countries debate among company directors on best places to establish such banks.
  - Brazil Clippings, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 156)
    Contains newspaper clippings relating to Berent Friele's interests in Brazil. Includes a pamphlet detailing nuclear energy use in Brazil.
  - Brazil Clippings and Capital Remittances, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 157)
    Includes the translation of a Brazilian bill of law decreeing powers to the executive branch of government over the economy and trade, particularly concerning remittance regulations. Also includes details of a similar bill passed in Colombia. Includes many documents focusing on US investors lobbying for less restriction on foreign investments in Brazil. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Brazil Petroleum Legislation, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 158)
    Includes news bulletin which states that Brazil has passed a law obliging all manufacturers of rubber goods to invest 20% of their annual profits in planting new rubber trees as well as important news on the passage of a bill focusing on the production of petroleum in Brazil. Includes photograph of Brazilian President Getulio Vargas and newspaper clippings.
  - Brazilian American Chamber of Commerce, 1970-1979 (Box 11, Folder 159)
    Includes correspondence, newspaper articles, and pamphlets relating to David Rockefeller and his involvement alongside Friele in US-Brazilian relations, including his distinction as being chosen as "Man of the Year" by the Brazilian-American Chamber of Commerce, of which Friele is an Honorary President.
  - Brazilian American Roundtable, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 160)
    Contains a speech delivered by Berent Friele and hosted by the Brazilian Institute of New York University on US-Brazilian relations.
  - Brazilian Companies, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 161)
    Features profiles for a compilation of businesses in Brazil, including farms and locations suitable for new business ventures. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Brazilian Economy, 1952-1959 (Box 11, Folder 162)
    Documents, files, and correspondence relating to various aspects of the Brazilian Economy, including a plan to establish wheat fields in a region of the country. Contains a pamphlet entitled Combate a Inflacao: O Valor Do Cruzeiro (Combating Inflation: The Value of the Cruzeiro) as well as a weekly newsletter by the American Chamber of Commerce for Brazil.
  - Brazilian Remittance Regulations, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 163)
    Memorandums, news bulletins, and documents of the National Foreign Trade Council pertaining to the repatriation of foreign capital which had been invested in Brazil. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Center for Latin American Relations and Americas Foundation, 1977-1981 (Box 11, Folder 164)